#### Contact

rahulkumaran313@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/rahularulkumaran (LinkedIn) github.com/rahulkumaran (Other) rahulkumaran.com (Blog)

### Top Skills

Python

С

C++

### Languages

Telugu (Native or Bilingual) Hindi (Elementary) Tamil (Native or Bilingual)

#### Certifications

Al Workflow: Data Analysis and Hypothesis Testing

Microsoft Technical Associate - Machine Learning

Kharagpur Winter of Code 2018

Runner Up - OpenCode18

#### Honors-Awards

Runner up in Opencode18 Successfully completed KWoC

Got Selected for India's Biggest Student Hackathon - Hack In The North

Data Science Hackathon - 5th place Microsoft Student Associate

#### **Publications**

Real Time Predictions Of Adverse Digressions In Critical and Noisy Industrial Processes Using LSTMs

# Rahul Arulkumaran

Co-founder @ Widhya | Helping students get employment opportunities | Helping companies hire quality talent | Speaker | Hyderabad

## Summary

Currently a Bachelor's student pursuing my major in Computer Science from Mahindra Ecole Centrale. Coming up with solutions to problems piques my interest and keeps me working day in and day out. I come with a plethora of experience in the startup ecosystem. Having worked in multiple startups since the beginning of engineering as a Growth Hacker and Data Scientist, I have also Co-Founded 2 startups, namely, FreeFlo(closed) and Widhya.

My mission, my goal is to make a change in the education system by allowing students to learn differently by adopting a "Learning by Doing" approach. That is what my startup, Widhya focuses on. I handle the Technology, Data Science, Outreach & Marketing teams at Widhya. I'm primarily a technology person with a massive appetite to learn and work in both technological and non-technological fields.

My core competencies are the following:

Algorithms, Front-end & Backend development, API Development, Machine Learning, Statistics, Data Science, Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Data Storytelling, Natural Language Processing, Strategising, Marketing, Sales, Leadership.

I like to call myself a Full-Stack Data Leader because I can take care of Data Science teams and ensure the whole pipeline is managed and implemented smoothly and efficiently. From gathering data to deriving insights to building statistical and predictive models and finally deploying them, I can handle it all.

In the past, I've worked on various projects in the verticals of FinTech, Healthcare, MarkTech, E-Commerce, and EdTech. I love performing research on a large scale, and I focus on a result-driven approach. My works have been selected for publications and presentations at various local, national, and international conferences.

Being a vocal supporter of Open-Source software and development, I actively contribute to many organizations like Sendgrid, GatsbyJS and Microsoft. My achievements include winning and completing many Open Source challenges and hackathons, organized by IIT-Kharagpur, IIIT-Allahabad, and JNTUH. I am also one of the winners of the world's largest student hackathon, the Smart India Hackathon 2019 edition.

I strongly believe in giving back to the community and love helping the community using technology. In the past, I've has been recognized for my works and have been awarded the:

- 21 under 21 award by Girlscript India Foundation
- Karmaveer Chakra award instituted by the United Nations

## Experience

Widhya Co-Founder & CEO November 2018 - Present (1 year 10 months)

Hyderabad, Telangana, India

- Handling the Data Science, Strategy and Marketing teams at Widhya.
- Introduced a key initiative, the Widhya Beta Program, that allows Widhya to focus on creating content/Missions over open source projects. Focused on a crowd sourcing strategy to develop more quality Missions in shorter time frames.
- Generated 2 key reports that assist us in approaching students and potential partner companies with metrics regarding Widhya's effectiveness and performance so far and has helped convince and onboard 5 companies in one month.
- Raised over INR 2L in revenue in the first 5 operational months.
- Drove a zero-cost marketing strategy which resulted in sales of over INR 50k in a span of 2 days.

Page 2 of 5

- Reached over 500 active users on the platform during the private beta.

GenY Labs
Data Science Intern
June 2019 - August 2019 (3 months)
Hyderabad, Telangana, India

FreeFlo
Co-Founder and CEO
March 2018 - August 2019 (1 year 6 months)
Hyderabad, Telangana, India

FreeFlo is a start up, that currently focuses on creating websites from scratch and selling basic website templates. Apart from this we help engineering students with their engineering projects related to basic coding and logic, Data

Science and Machine Learning. We'll soon be expanding into other fields too.

Council of Scientific and Industrial Research Data Science Intern May 2019 - June 2019 (2 months)

Work From Home

- Working on a project to spread awareness about mental health under Dr. Sukant Khurana at the Central Drug Research Institute (CSIR-CDRI).
- The initial part of this project and my role was to validate the results and build a more robust dataset for the ongoing research at the organisation.
- Started with collecting data corresponding to various politicians and schools in Uttar Pradesh and slowly inching towards collecting data of schools for every country in South Asia.
- The data was collected by scraping various websites and running them in parallel to achieve results in a faster manner.

Eat My News

5 months

Assistant Vice President - National Marketing February 2019 - May 2019 (4 months)

Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Working towards strategies to grow the network of Eat My News all around the country.

- Responsible to increase Eat My News' brand awareness
- Responsible to create partnerships with various media houses

Manager - National Expansions
January 2019 - February 2019 (2 months)

Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Helping Eat My News gain a greater reach around India. Making more people aware about EMN and getting them on the Board Of Young Leaders. Onboarding people and helping with selection process.

Mahindra École Centrale Undergraduate Researcher September 2018 - May 2019 (9 months) Hyderabad

Working under Prof. Amitava Das on understanding the process of radicalization by various extremist groups around the world through social media platforms and predicting whether a user is vulnerable or not. The dataset has been built from scratch and 70 primary have been identified and manually annotated to see how lethal and influential they are. These 70 targets have been used to get more data points. We consider their first and second hop network and predict user vulnerablility depending on a number of network dynamics measures.

Verzeo
Machine Learning Intern
May 2018 - June 2018 (2 months)
Hyderabad, Telangana, India

- Worked on building and learning about various machine learning models.
- Took a couple of datasets and used multiple machine learning algorithms to understand which was the best.
- Worked on SMS and Email Spam Filters.

TEDxMahindraEcoleCentrale Head - Web Development Team July 2017 - May 2018 (11 months) Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Helping MEC's TEDx team to create a website for the upcoming edition of TEDx. For the previous edition of TEDxMahindraÉcoleCentrale, we used WordPress but for the upcoming edition, we'll be doing it from scratch.

MCaffeine Growth Hacker November 2016 - May 2017 (7 months) Hyderabad, Telangana, India Main role is to ensure more and more people get to know about the brand and also suggest the company ways to create brand awareness. Study various e-commerce platforms and find out how that would help benefit the company. Taking care of the sales angle to using various sales strategies.

# Education

WorldQuant University

Master of Science - MSc, Financial Engineering · (2020 - 2022)

Mahindra École Centrale
Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.), Computer Science · (2016 - 2020)

Sri Chaitanya Junior Kalasala Intermediate, MPC · (2014 - 2016)